Oliver Doepner

Halifax, Nova Scotia work.odoepner [at] gmail.com http://oliver.doepner.net/

IT Skills

- Programming languages: Expert: Java, bash Sometimes: Scala, Clojure, Groovy, JRuby, JavaScript
- Web Technologies:
 HTML5, CSS3, XML/XSL,
 JQuery, JSP / Servlets,
 JSF / Facelets, Spring Web
 Flow, GWT, Wicket, SVG,
 Unicode / i18n
- Java Technologies: Java 5/6/7, JEE, Spring, Hibernate/JPA, JDBC, JMS, JavaMail, Swing, RMI, Web Services, JAXB, JAX-WS, Ehcache, JGroups
- Software Engineering:
 OOP / OOD, UML, Design
 Patterns, MVC, Refactoring,
 Test-Driven Development,
 Extreme Programming (XP),
 Agile / Iterative methods
- Project Management : Confluence, JIRA, Bugzilla, Aegis, LibreOffice
- Development Tools:

 Eclipse, IntelliJ, Netbeans,
 Aptana, Vim, Maven, Ant,
 Aegis, SVN, CVS, Perforce,
 git/mercurial, Teamcity,
 Hudson/Jenkins, Sonar,
 Nexus, JUnit, HtmlUnit
- Servers / Databases:
 Weblogic, JBoss, Tomcat,
 Jetty, Oracle, Postgres,
 MySQL, Apache Derby
- Operating Systems:
 Debian GNU/Linux, Ubuntu,
 OpenSolaris, MacOS X,
 Windows XP + 7, Cygwin

Professional Profile

I am a software engineer and IT professional with a focus on object oriented development and design, preferrably using Java and Open Source components.

My <u>IT skills</u> are based on 20+ years of hands-on programming experience, <u>professional software development</u> since 1995 and a broad <u>academic background</u>.

I lead teams to quality results and customer satisfaction through practices like testdriven development, continuous integration, frequent code reviews and controlled refactoring.

I have <u>developed applications</u> for digital service providers, oil & gas, steel industry, postal services, financial institutions, government agencies and various mediumsized businesses.

Education and Studies

University of the Saarland, Germany

1998-2002 State examination in Mathematics and German

1995-1998 German 'Vordiplom' - like a BSc - in Computational Linguistics

IBM Scientific Centre, Heidelberg, Germany

Summer 1996 Research project in Computer Assisted Language Learning (CALL)

University of Sussex, United Kingdom

1994-1995 ERASMUS scholar, Certificate in Mathematics & Informatics

Technische Universität Darmstadt, Germany

1991-1994 German 'Vordiplom' - like a BSc - in Mathematics and Informatics

1991-1993 Intermediate Examination in <u>History</u>

Claus-von-Stauffenberg Schule, Germany

until 1990 High School Diploma, highest GPA of the school year

Work experience

CGI, Halifax, Nova Scotia

2008-now Senior Consultant / Team Lead: Design, Implementation and unit testing of Enterprise Java systems, Java / JEE consulting.

SupportSoft, Halifax, Nova Scotia

2007-2008 Software Engineer: Design, Implementation and Testing of large J2EE project, expert for JMS, Object Caching, WS security, Date/Time handling, DAOs, Log4J, JUnit

iKu Systemhaus AG, Saarbrücken

2002-2004, Software Engineer and Project Lead: Swing applications, web 2005-2006 applications, client/server systems, mail server components

University of the Saarland, Maths Teaching Library

1999-2001 Development of an OPAC using MySQL and Apache Jserv, Administration of Debian GNU/Linux systems

i2c Systems, Bad Homburg

2000 Requirement Specification and Architecture Design for Multiple Language Support in J2EE applications

DFKI Saarbrücken, Language Technology Lab

1995-1996 Research assistance, Tool development for Human Name extraction, Website automation with Perl

KfW Bankengruppe, Frankfurt/Main

1995-1999 Object Oriented Development with Gupta/Centura and Oracle, Code Repository metadate generation with C++

Desktop Display Ltd., Brighton, UK

1995 Web Application Project using CGI on NCSA webserver

Software Projects

In all of these projects I worked as principal / core developer or team lead:

CGI - Capital Markets: As a senior software engineer and consultant I work for a large international client in the capital markets sector on advanced Java features of complex systems and provide technical guidance to our developer teams in business domains like Clearing or Risk Management.

[Java 6 + 7, Concurrency, Clustering, JPA/Hibernate, Spring, Oracle Coherence, JGroups, JUnit, Intellij IDEA, Atlassian Tools (Confluence, JIRA, Crucible, Fisheye), Subversion, Maven, Jenkins, Nexus, TOAD, Oracle, Sybase, Linux shell

CGI - Oil & Gas AMS: As senior software engineer I was responsible for the technical quality and efficiency of our service delivery to a major Canadian oil & gas company. We support and enhance 150+ Java applications, mostly webapps in a Tomcat environment, working with a team of 5 - 10 Java Developers.

[Java 6, Tomcat 6, IntelliJ IDEA, Struts / JSP, GWT, Spring, Hibernate, iBatis, Apache POI, Ant, RMI, Atlassian Dev Tools (Confluence, JIRA, Bamboo), JQuery, JRuby on Rails, CVS]

CGI - Wealth Core Platform: This solution for the financial sector was one of the biggest Software Development projects at CGI. I served as Technical Lead for the UI layer, designing and implementing a UI framework using Spring Web Flow / JSF. I coordinated up to 10 developers across four CGI locations.

[Java 6, Spring Web Flow, JSF 1.2 / Facelets, Tomcat 6, Spring, JAXB, JUnit, Eclipse, Maven, Hudson/Jenkins, SVN]

CGI - Canada Post - BDT: Business Desktop 2.0 is Canada Post's Electronic Shipping Tools (EST) application. It is a client/server Java application that prints all paperwork required for business mailings and shipments and automates the shipping process.

[Java 5, Spring, XML/XSL, XSL-FO, Apache FOP, TestNG, PdfBox, Weblogic, IntelliJ IDEA, Maven, SVN]

ServiceGateway: SupportSoft's enterprise solution for remote configuration and management of home networks. Built for the DSL forum standard TR-069, it is used by DSPs throughout the world.

[J2EE, Weblogic, JBoss, EJB, JMS, Web Services (XFire), EhCache, Oracle 10g, Perforce, Adobe Flex]

SPONTS: Email proxy for spam and virus protection, online backup, email monitoring and email security [Java, SMTP/S, POP3/S, IMAP/S, Apache Tomcat, Hibernate, Apache Derby, I18n, Embedded Linux]

LI Inspektor: Simulates email procedures to test Lawful Interception (LI) systems for legal compliance.

[Java, JSF/MyFaces, Hibernate, JavaMail, Apache FTP, POP3/S, IMAP/S, SMTP/S]

Bodward: An email monitoring store that plugs into Lawful Interception solutions.

[Java, Apache FTP API, Java RMI, TCP networking, Hibernate, Apache Derby, dom4j]

emVisu: A client/server solution to collect and visualize measured temperatures of heavy plates for Dillinger Hütte GTS, one of the biggest steel manufacturers in Europe.

[Java Swing, Custom Swing Widgets / LayoutManager, RMI, JMS, JDBC, MySQL]

AutoCool: Distributed steel plate cooling process control and visualization, also for Dillinger Hütte GTS.

[Java Swing, Input Validation Framework, DAO Pattern, JDBC, MySQL]

HSA Control: GUI application to control a steel plate branding machine for Dillinger Hütte GTS.

[Java Swing, JMS, RMI, Custom Datagram Protocol, C struct parsing]

Plakatdrucker: Webshop for print products: calculations, customer management, upload and messaging. [Apache Tomcat, JSP Custom Tags, CSS, Apache FileUpload, JavaMail, JDBC]

lceWorld : Monitoring and config of RAID systems (embedded webserver, RMI interface, Swing client)

[Java, Tomcat, JSP Custom Tags, CSS, RXTX/Comm, RMI, Java Swing, Swing DnD]

CashTrend: Calculation and generation of financial OpenOffice documents based on customer data.

[Java Swing, OpenOffice Java API, JDBC, MySQL]

MdBib: Online Public Access Catalogue (OPAC) for a library of at the University of the Saarland.

[Apache Tomcat, Apache Jserv, Java Servlets, MySQL]

Infrastrukt: Migration of the mainframe based IT of KfW Bankengruppe to a client/server infrastructure.

[OOD/OOP, Gupta/Centura, Win32 API, C++, IBM RS/6000, IBM IMS, Oracle DB]